hello and welcome it's August 16 2023
we're in the collective Behavior
discussion section of the active
inference for the social sciences course
in 2023.
so perhaps let us all go around
and give a opening
introduction and or reflection
and see who joins and what happens from
there but just so that everybody has
said hello
Jim hi everyone I'm Brynn and uh 9 pm in
South Africa and uh
yeah just excited to be here see what
happens
hi I'm Andrew I'm a graduate student in
Indiana and
um
I guess my
field of uh interest now is the
Knowledge Management and I think that
figuring out how we collectively learn
and can
um
share information my teacher is a really
interesting topic and I'd like to see
how this would apply
Regina and I'm performing with them now
that I'm living in Spain
studying and doing experiments related
to this topic and trying to learn a
little bit of the
um Theory that's behind it so it can you
know Advance better
I'm excited
hello my name is Sasha I'm calling in
from California I'm also a graduate
student
um yeah just really enjoyed the spirited
presentation last week I'm looking
forward to a discussion
all right well
how about anyone can
give a first reflection on Collective
Behavior or what
what was their
thought or context before and where are
they at as we kind of begin yeah Regina
okay so I just want to make sure that I
understand because I took like two big
lessons from your lesson right and the
first one is that
um you know this this famous model of
active inference that has the agent and
the environment and the Markov blanket
in the middle right and just interacts
with everything right so I think what I
got from what you discussed
um maybe I didn't have a good definition
of an agent but first that you can have
that agent not be just an individual
but also your definition of an
individual changes depending on what you
want to study in the behavior right so
an agent can be an aunt it can be an
ecosystem it can be an eye looking at
something or it can be a as a society
for example and I think that's a big
take for me because it changes a lot the
concept of how to study things and use
active imprints just by changing how big
the agent can be
so I don't know if like I got that right
right so first that clarification
so what is an agent
yeah so I don't know if there's like a
formal definition of an agent in active
inference right but uh if we
if we want to study whatever we want to
study because um I'll study because I
have to do that's like my goal whatever
I'm doing so I want to study whatever I
have to choose what's going to be my
agent and the environment it has
so choosing the agent you can do it to
create a model or to make an experiment
whatever but
um the choice you make it will depend on
your
in what you understand an individual or
as an agent I think so right
awesome anyone have a thought on that no
but if if I continued you know just to
add something else and this will be my
my
um and then I'm thinking is that
um
also a big problem that we have or I
think I have is that since I am part of
the environment
um you know you know the perspective of
whoever is studying whatever it is it's
also going to be an effect in it so
maybe maybe scientists already decided
but I don't know that we can never have
an objective way of studying something
if you're part of the environment of the
agent
so I don't know we already forgot it or
we already decided that's it we cannot
have objective observations of behavior
in general
but you know you always think about like
the agent environment and you studying
it as something else but this something
else is also effect in it so I see that
as a problem or maybe something that has
to be said like we are not objective
because we're part of what it's
affecting our ages in the behavior
collectively too
so those are the the thoughts I have to
share
uh Regina I'm uh I'm also new to to all
of this so my preliminary understanding
of of orders and agent is uh anything
that has any good reason uh to
self-evidence and to itself or to
survive
um that doesn't want to dissipate that
might delineate the boundary of what an
agent is that then sits at
uh um
the boundaries with which it um will
as you described start interacting
with the world with the environment
so if something as I understand it if
something has a reason to go on being to
survive
um
um then it is an agent in the world
okay but but that agent could be
anything right like
is that what you're saying right like if
he wants to survive it can be an ant
surviving individually or a cell or or a
group okay yeah that's a good that's
like a good definition
okay
yeah Sasha
um great points Regina
um so much to say there
um something that I have experienced
with um as a researcher in biology is
deciding the kind of
um
the statistics or sampling approach to
use whether we're taking you know one
cell from one individual or we're taking
many cells from many individuals and how
to do the statistics and kind of
um sampling approach on that
um that is a you know an evergreen
question that we're always reevaluating
to see um
how to think about the independencies
within biological systems
um
and then another thing that you
mentioned was about the individual being
part of the ecosystem and that makes me
think a lot about complexity science and
something that um is addressed there in
uh thinking about the interplay of the
scientists and what they're studying
yeah thank you for those points
especially I can
sorry I'm not raising my hand I'm just
I'm using it
that's okay can you say a bit more about
what you mean by complexity designs is
baby muted
oh can't speak at the moment
yeah
complexity science has looked at Asian
asia-based modeling as a fundamental
tool John Holland signals and boundaries
focusing on what
from an active inference side we might
say it's like message passing or
communication for the messages and then
boundaries with
the whole discussion around
the boundaries in the world map
territory map territory fallacy map
territory fallacy fallacy
doing iterative modeling
Sasha brought up limited experimental
resources in in the scientific setting
and that's kind of analogous to The
Limited energy budget or attentional
budget ultimately or just
decision-making budget
of uh
the kinds of active entities that
make sense to model the ones that kind
of have those uh characteristics
this is really the question of what
makes something first principles or what
are the first principles
one aspect of it as brought up
is the censoring of the persistence so
from the outside that's kind of like an
empiricists view of persistence like is
it measurable
but not saying that something is
necessarily that which is the
statistical tool and then the sort of
like inside out
implementation type
but
there's a lot more to say in that who
wants to
bring in some
New Angle or
how do they see Collective Behavior
why do we talk about Collective Behavior
why not just Behavior recognize that
behavior is multi-scale or or social
what's really being
communicated with the collective
I mean I I believe that we chose those
levels so we can make it more simple for
our brains to understand it because if
we talk about Collective Behavior
actually is the universe behaving and
the particles and everything right
so I don't know if that's a little bit
just based on I don't know what's the
word like just in the material world and
how it physically moves and that's like
deterministic or whatever right
but
um
I think us we chose to have those
limitations so we could understand the
world but also we should acknowledge
that are limited because we're part of
the system
I'm having a little trouble on my kind
of understanding the
I guess the where the
Schism lies between kind of the
the Markov blanket and uh the um well in
uh semiotics of like the animals uh
sensory experience
anyone have a maybe maybe someone could
uh I mean Daniel Dino
like the difference between that too
um can you be a little louder thank you
though Andrew anyone have a thought on
that
I'll bring in a definition of whom felt
then and then we can see but meanwhile
does anyone have a thought
sorry sorry I was just muted on Andrew
you're a little quiet
but um I'm gonna bring in a definition
of umvelt and then meanwhile does anyone
have a thought
I I hope I'm not uh
where the diluting Andrew's uh uh
question
um
but
I think a collective behavior in kind of
like a I don't know football team or
soccer team
um and what that provides
uh
the grip who is uh
share some common ethos and what that
does to the
how that regulates the their Collective
or individual and Collective free
energies
um during a match or throughout the
season and how that
that gives some
uh
yeah some charge to
uh some Investments because it's my team
against yours
and we have to
um try and win and so you know without
it without that Collective Behavior
um
it's it's might be far harder to achieve
the group's goals if they aren't able to
collaborate and share
um you know implicitly and explicitly
certain traits behaviors thoughts
feelings ideals ideologies whatever they
might be and how that's been
allows us to compete in the world
I I thought you think it's
yes okay okay I see what you're saying
uh especially because we're watching
over the World Cup right Women's World
Cup
yes it's very relevant yeah but I see
that in all the
there's things you've said it seems that
for your behavior needs to have like a
goal and I don't know if I if I agree
with that it's either survival or
winning
but main for me it's just something that
happens and maybe the consequences
surviving
but it's not the goal to survive or to
win the game
I mean in in the football it is right
but in general
um maybe there's no goal to the behavior
collectively
and just
just a thought
it's interesting
yeah all the great comments well the
paper of Connor Hines at all on the
collective Behavior as surprise
minimization
that points the way towards
using the actin fontology these kinds of
modeling approaches for Collective
behavioral situations
and really just recognizing them as a
certain type of Behavioral modeling the
simplest case might just be a single
closed system
all part of the
composition
that leads to
the ability to describe at very least
a lot of different kinds of systems just
like a linear model can describe a lot
of systems so then
it's also really interesting a topic
that came up in one of the recent
textbook groups
with what's normative about active
inference because the term of
uh the process Theory even of active
inference
being normative is mentioned multiple
times and that's definitely a topic that
connects to the social sciences one can
imagine the kind of Niche normativity or
niche regularities in a broad sense
and then the real minute particulars of
how they play out which kind of hints at
the kind of descriptive or causal
minimum
to start making some anything but toy
specific generative models
so it's been an interesting theme to see
even already in
avells and Ben's lectures and
discussions
this question between
description
process of describing
which is what I associated with
Professor Gordon's approach to ant
watching
how that descriptive process which is
what we can say that we have for active
inference just like a linear modeling
ecosystem could say about their linear
modeling in principle
um and how to then
articulate the normativities of the
framework
if that concept if that separation can
even exist
from the
uh Behavioral normativities
that include
the basis of social Fabric in
all different kinds of communities
here's another question so
what is the role of any technical detail
in in the social sciences
whether more on the statistical
connecting with data
or more category theoretic-like
just formal
what's the role of formal methods
in
different kinds of academic or practical
Expressions about social systems
doesn't matter at all
how we think about
a framework at all
well
for formalizing
um
aspects of a social system that I would
say that the purpose is for
communication
between individuals
because just
you know we can't verify that
well formalizing it is just setting a
system on top of what you're observing
um but there is no explicit
uh guarantee that you're saying
encompasses everything of the phenomena
you're observing
and
just
like you know kind of going back to
taoism of like the name that can be
named is not the true Eternal name and
so it's just a way of
you know it's it's a slice of what we
can observe
and
the way to um
you know maybe you can make predictions
or maybe you can generate something that
acts like
the the phenomena phenomena you're
observing but
um so it's just it's a way to kind of
it's just a way to kind of approximate
our understanding of some phenomena and
you have to slice it in a specific way
but also understanding that it is a
slice or you know it is a tangent line
that you're approximating as opposed to
encompassing the whole system from
verbalizing it
um I will uh maybe it's not the goal but
something that happens out of describing
any system like Andrew said it's like
um the goal to modify it or to
or to corrupt it in some way to gain
control or whatever we know the model
you know how to play the game kinda
so you write instructions and try to see
if you can
outsmart someone else I mean it sounds
kind of dark right but maybe it's one of
the goals to or something that just
happens out of knowing the rules that
nobody else knows
I mean I guess when you when you talk
about control there is a
there there is a shade that can be
um gained from that specific wording but
control in terms of you know control
theory or you know that that comes from
electrical engineering it's really just
what
um
what shapes the behavior or what are
they what are the inputs that drive the
the behavior and when you're talking
about control
it's really just about
um well if you change these inputs how
does that change the end behavior and so
you can actually
you know from electrical engineering of
controlling a
some sort of electromechanical system
but then you can make analogous
statements on like control into society
which doesn't necessarily mean like the
dark negative control but like you know
maybe there's some pathological behavior
in in a society or uh you know even
pathological
um
pathological responses within the brain
and it's like well what is what is
driving that and is it possible to to
change those those
change the drivers of that to have
something that is a more
beneficial to the system
yeah just just to add
um to what Andrew's saying because it
matters
sometimes how you manipulate
um uh you know
a a system or it matters how you affect
a brain so it cannot be random I mean uh
you know we've come a long way
for example from lobotomy uh which had
disastrous effects and and you you it
matters to a system how you affect it
and so to know
more formally
uh the most effective way to create a
desired effect whatever that might be
and it's essential that it's not just
kind of poking and prodding there's like
that that has
[Music]
as much as that has is part of the
scientific method to update that method
in accordance with what you're learning
so it is is important
um
no I think we're both writing it doesn't
have to be dark but also something else
that Andrew said about predicting I
think that's what also the the big goals
trying to predict whether to be prepared
to
or or
just to I mean it couldn't be to control
right but if you if you can somehow
predict
how people respond to days or how a
system will behave in this other
scenario you can you know change what
the input is or
prepare for whatever comes I guess
yeah
a lot of great points some of the
commonly held not not equally by
everyone everyone but
some of the attendance of science
being to explain predict design and
control
where explanation and prediction
are on the pathway towards uh systems
designing and and maintenance and other
other words that people can add but
that's the pragmatic utility oriented
View
which doesn't have to be an absolutist
view but certainly there are regimes of
attention socially now and seemingly for
long long times where people were
wanting to
retain and to constrain the variance
distribution
on what we would say is their generative
model some Norm
and then other times engaging in these
functions and that instrumentalist usage
of active inference is like we're going
to be able to model it
with
a pretty minimum
framework that's commonly used in
statistical systems where some things we
observe and some we don't
and at least we know and how all the
pieces are connected
and then that is an artifact in
model-based design
as people
um
develop that line through time socially
just like probably has been always the
case for a complex
projects and scientific collaboration
there's a few other interesting pieces
yeah please please
I'm just I'm just wondering if well now
that I'm thinking out loud
um isn't that like a problem
or confirmation bias right like there's
a paper of in here here because we
create the knowledge and we tell
everyone the knowledge this is the model
this is how everything behaves and then
we update our knowledge about it and
then we look for everything to just you
know confirm it and
and yeah
maybe there's another system that will
not let us be getting knowledge so
slowly because if everybody just agrees
on something we teach it to everyone and
we confirm the model and then we just
try to look for evidence for that model
then we go slowly if there's any better
thing or better model that comes along
you have a lot to say about that like
if we believe that trees exist or that
people exist and then we come to see
them so there's kind of this sense where
problem confirmation bias which I think
is a great term a great topic to bring
in
with definitely also what's called like
the Golden Nail syndrome or something if
all you have is the hammer then
everything's a nail
and there's definitely attention there
because it's like
how much of what you can do are you
supposed to do
something that you can't do
or but then at least you could do what
you needed to do to get there so that's
actually within your scope of what you
can do so it's not that there are things
that you can't do that you can't do
if just from a measurement first
membership
so like
how does it look or how do we recognize
across systems
or how do we have awareness in
situations as limited individuals
who do have all of these
cognitive phenomena
how to make decisions or sense making or
infrastructure or whatever it is the
social
Ness the the system of interest of the
social sciences make that and then dot
dot dot normatively what
I think it's the sun protection built
into into uh
the problem of confirmation bias because
all knowledge generation is happening in
in a in an open system
and so there's always going to be an
agent outside of your
your own mind and it's and what it's
perceiving that that can then challenge
or add to the
you know like the the the super the the
LK 99
um
uh
semiconductors that have there's been
all the rage recently and and how
um at the scientists have now kind of
um discredited it uh quite convincingly
and it's because of this open they might
have had degrees of confirmation bias
that they were egging each other on but
it's it's ultimately been refuted which
is uh
this built-in kind of protection because
it's all operating in a in a in an open
system fortunately
yeah a lot to see there uh Monday
morning reviewer touring
how how do we again go from
any given description of a communicative
event
like the kind of specific unfolding of
the LK 99 narrative
as yet uncompleted
in in the minds of sum which is real
enough
to be real socially
and uh so how do we go from any
descriptive anything about that
total observation
to core screening
then
how do we
come to uh work with that interface with
what whatever that is hands that to us
what is the social behavior
what are some some classic
or some novel
social behaviors
maybe ones that seem pretty obvious
due to recency bias
I'll just mention one aspect that Andrew
and I have also talked about is the auto
poetic nature of Information Systems
Andrew do you have any thought on this
or about where Auto places comes into
like social sciences or these kinds of
models
they're genuine Andrew just left a note
that he's uh okay okay
we just wasn't looking at the time funny
stuff anyone else have a thought on that
okay just just to kind of carry it
forward then basically the the ability
of social systems that include
written Niche modification cumulative
culture
they're increasing
extent of control
as discussed earlier that that
definitely is a bit of a overloaded or
at least doubly meant term in different
settings because it can just simply mean
modeling it with control theory which is
pretty limited philosophical statements
relative to any statistical method or
control like
the kind that people are unhappy with
and the kind that's described in
thinking like a state
and a lot of other works that I know Mao
and Lorena and aval are going to be
definitely going into more
uh detail
on so when societies can model
and introspect or or self-reflect
formally
much better
and that can happen through
anything from
free and open source Federated protocols
there's many limited formats
of self-meaning making but cryptography
definitely allows those Explorations and
that doesn't necessarily mean computer
cryptography that could also be like
linguistic encoding
and all these other ways of of niche
sub differentiation
in multi-scale systems
you just did not see a system that is
cookie cutter
it's very rare in ecosystems
there's algal blooms and things like
that
so when we really think about the
Developmental and the cognitive and the
selective niche
which is a concept that Axel constant
and others have differentiated in some
of their like ecological octave
inference work
like that Niche is very embodied
extended and cultured etc etc
it's just like a kind of cool direct way
to
open up to that challenge of modeling
and just
bring some
closures
with different accounts or
compatibilities with different accounts
so like all just to give one random
example but maybe it'd be interesting
what what other people think
all the Expressions that people make in
Social settings
can just simply be their expressions or
modeled as such
that is
in one way implicitly
what was always in play
but now
it's describable and legible
and autonomous so
how do we take this active inference
Collective Behavior
crossover and think about what it really
means
in how we're going to be like thinking
differently even just this discussion
forward or like more locally are our
understandings with Collective Behavior
or with behavior
um
Daniel can you ask the the question
again I I didn't actually catch the
um how do we the quiz start how do we
start to adapt
some of these General comments
or or frames that are in some ways
disconnected from descriptions of real
systems
how do we think about that
and and what it means
now
what is on the
yeah good that's okay
uh do you mean on the document in front
of us or these these these disconnected
things in front of us that on on the on
the document
I don't know whatever you think or
whatever you want to say
okay
yeah I I think there's a lot uh and I
again I hope I'm not
uh
you know and fully understanding the
question I hope I'm not steering away uh
too much but I gotta had a general sense
of what I think you were saying and
I think it's an enormous uh problem with
the amount of
um information sharing
um just in a in a with let's just take
uh the general uh generative models of
um social media and all of the platforms
that are available to us how much
information we are privy to in any given
uh moments
um
and
I'm kind of forgetting the question that
I that you asked um but but how do you
it's almost as if there is such a
a high rate of information and data flow
that it's really hard to know what to do
with all of it and
and at least as a human being I'm not
saying for machines but um
but uh as a psychologist I'm certainly
interested in
how humans are able to tolerate and
respond to
um
the amount and rate of information
that's all okay
this is not the first time this happens
right like we went from talking to
writing information
then everyone wrote their information
and then we have books and then we have
libraries and that's all available and
again we have access if you can read
right to all the information in the
world so
we adapted to
I don't know to get careers so we could
specify in
which type of information you are going
to know more so maybe we need some sort
of new
career types I don't know more
specifications
with more information
not uh is the rate of information
flowing increases and not is it not
exponential is it not uh
um I know it's it's a crazy amount that
our brains cannot do anything about it
so we have to do multi-disciplinary
things and work together with others if
we want to make something
but
yeah I don't know maybe we will die of
excess of information
how did people feel like active
inference bring something to the
discussion relative to
[Music]
how they want to work towards
ants yeah well isn't that the
provocative question too
but like any system that's that that's
the question everyone is gonna have
their own memes and themes and and
systems that they have spent time with
and did field work with and all this
other like particularity
because a system that doesn't have
particularity is just not going to be
hosting a broad enough Niche for for
phenotypic diversity
uh it's just riding on the edge of a
razor instead of more like a fabric that
continues to unfold I think
there's a lot of work to do with the
social sciences and active inference
just from what I was like reading
trying to find things for this
um discussion
and just I personally wondered what is
is Meaningful or interesting
or useful what's epistemic and pragmatic
value for difference
audiences How does it go from kind of
bringing citations that were not linked
together
in
some
more theoretical or more generative
model oriented work in active inference
like epistemic foraging or the infra
ants model
or
any other kind of specific model what
are these different kinds of scientific
artifacts do
for who
I guess I'm still learning very
uh
very
kind of crude be cuddling along here
Daniel with to try and answer that
because it's I've quickly realized that
the field is it's so
it has so much
um the the free energy principle uh the
Bayesian brain
even just to psychology has so much
applicability and everyone's seen
everyone I meet at these discussions is
coming at it from a different angle
um and it can be a bit confusing to hear
how other people
uh are applying it to how other people
are
um making use of it
um in all manner of ways and so I'm
still learning how to apply
um to kind of ring fence the free energy
principle and connect it to uh
psychological processes including
Collective behavior and because there's
a lot of Psychopathology in group think
in in Collective Behavior but I'm also
very very interested in its application
at the interface of
um what happens between a a therapist
and a patient
and and I'm often unlike other
um professions who seem who are just by
nature of the scientific method
um are able to extract
a lot more data to work with to analyze
to um uh um
you know um in a
that's very hard to do I feel very
limited
um other than just making kind of
theoretical leaps and inferences about
how to apply
um uh the free energy principle to
psychology
um
uh it's I can't have a session with my
brain hooked up to an fmri machine to
get data and to see uh when a patient
says
that's a spike on the the spike trains
which represents um you know surprisal
and we can then solve for that in some
way I'm I don't have access to that sort
of data flow so it feels limited but I'm
still learning how to apply it
um
yeah and trying to collaborate with
colleagues on that the influence group
what are people wondering about
Collective Behavior
even if we're totally of course not
going to address it but just what what
are the kinds of things that people
what makes you look up Collective
Behavior
instead of just Behavior or individual
foreign
safety and need to belong
for me it's um
I think that um
it depends for where you come from and
the country you are but there are places
that are more Collective and there are
places that are more individualistic and
I think mostly non-western countries
have a lot of collective Behavior or
knowledge and
periods already right that they already
knew these things that we think are new
for us right how the
Collective thing works for example I
don't know you don't make a decision for
yourself you make a decision for the
group like marrying you marry because
you want an audition you want to
interact with someone or other group and
that's something that affects the the
collective not just you so arrange
marriage makes sense something like that
right so for me making that decision
about individual Collective comes from
understanding that I don't know there
are other places that are already ahead
in what Collective means in terms of
human beings and how to interact
and the Western Wall we have all these
individualistic thing which is very
interesting because why do we have the
same species and then we have very
different approaches of how to
understand ourselves in terms of what an
individual is and why it matters
yes there's so much loaded
on different understandings among people
including even the the essence of the
social
which is who are people and what is the
the
obligation and how do we view that that
relationship
that's a very
very deep area and and again the part
that just kept returning to me in the
lecture and when I was trying to think
about how to how to even reflect part of
uh this very large area
is like what is the adjective doing
and what what is what's the reference
point by which this is being said
in the speech acts like people often
will dismiss I don't mean to
um you know straw people but dismiss
Collective Behavior by saying well we
are explaining individual Behavior
what are you explaining Beyond The Nest
mates in The Colony
and then the exterior like that is it
and so that can feel like to looking at
the same thing from two different sides
and there are different methods like
some methods blur over individuals a lot
more
like statistical methods or that might
correspond to demographics and then on
the other hand like more agent-based
models
but how much
variability in what shared variability
and why General synchranies
amongst different Quantum reference
frames all these nested
if these possibilities
that
are are grounded in wanting to explore
mathematical and scientific
possibilities
as as the literature of linear
regression is full of so many incredible
extensions and and and similar
and then that's
I I think what the course is
even beginning to
to try to express and what I understand
in the works of the other teachers like
a lot of your backgrounds and and
everything like that
is
where is that
moment where it is not only science
because science is not simply the social
so science has an activity and then as
there's a diffusion away from science
and I think that or or at least that
relationship between social and science
is right there in the title maybe that's
kind of like a science Majors take but
it but it is itself in a way
a um
presenting a dilemma
with what science means there and then
that's the frame game who's doing social
science who's doing not social science
and that's that's where
um in in the culture here I'm sitting in
slash in the technical side of that it
is related to statistics and formality
it's the xkcd comic
and the way that formalisms and and
details
are taken as
under some
regimes of attention basically
definitive
and yet there's like a yearning and a
counterbalancing that's expressed also
in many ways
and so that's
and science maybe some people feel like
certain social scientific methods that's
like not far enough in this Dimension
and then the others feel like they're
too far in this direction
but it's like
just like any uh like that academic
field let alone any other community of
diverse agents like of course there's
going to be distributions
of perspectives at different times
by those different perspectives and you
know
yeah
Daniel could do you think uh
these first principles
would be able to explain why an ant
colony exists uh I know that was your
um kind of area of interest of study uh
why an ant colony exists uh in in the
way that it is executive operating as a
collective and why
um another
um animal is able to survive and achieve
its goals
uh
as an individual uh only relying on the
environment and its actions and
Sensations to get its needs met into no
doubt minimize its um free energy but
could first principles
explain why the one has to survive as a
group and the other has to survive or is
able to survive
um under different conditions
yeah that's a super interesting question
it's it's very core to this individual
individuation
and multi-scale individuation concept
like is the nest made the individual and
then the colony is the social because
then for sure it's super collaborative
or is the colony of the organism and
massmates are tissues and then are they
social across Colony boundaries not
where I was in Arizona but they're often
friendly across different species and
they avoided conflict more often than
not so it's like what and then go why
does it even matter what's happening on
this plot of lands
in this in this area from like a
biomimicry perspective
we might learn new algorithms it's a
Sandbox for learning new techniques and
observation all these other like
richnesses so it's to say that like what
comes away from that science
that makes it social science
and I think there's a lot of
disciplinary ways of understanding that
which which I'm definitely not expert in
in the um professional Fields like like
counseling
um but probably in in all the different
Humanities and histories and all these
other fields
all these different Maps
the kind of social
um
the epistemic organizing question
and then the social organizing question
yeah and and the way like Technologies
also in that tangle
and yeah someone pointed out like this
is not a new problem
and uh but then it's like well what
parts are new and then what's our model
by which we're saying that it's like new
or too individualist or too Collective
on what scale
what if they're like really
collectivists at this scale but not at
this scale
or another an example of an ambiguous
or at least like um
polysomis
phenotype of colonies is in some
colonies there's partial reproductive
activation of like non-reproductive
Mass mates
and that has often been modeled from
like a position of like zero is the law
and how are they cheating above this but
it's also been approached from a colony
level
strategic bed hedging
so without super deep knowledge of
really some of the specifics of the
regularities that that Colony algorithm
had to persist
for so long and to have gotten swept off
the table if it was even it's like
that's that's a very integrated problem
so it helps you approach Collective
systems and and learn about them but
it's like
there's a lot to say about humidity loss
in foraging and humidity loss isn't even
the whole picture
and human foraging is a lot more
sophisticated
from just like a perception cognition
influence perspective
so
those are just some ant related thoughts
but it just centers a lot of discussions
that really matter
and I think the really interesting piece
is not always in the way
that they're thought to by some
yeah and it's and it's very hard to get
any kind of
cross-pollination with OTC caused
pollination
studying One agent it's it's quite for
at least in my mind very difficult to
kind of generalize things across
different agents um it starts getting a
bit
uh
yeah tricky to infer
one collector's uh
what how and why and how they survive
and how another agent does It's Tricky
so I I'm almost
human beings as hard as they are to
study and just try and run with it as
far as possible
yeah
otherwise it's just
information overload
body is a complex place too
and digital technology virtuality
these are such
um richly developed topics in the social
sciences I only know the tiniest amount
from
but I think that through
participation and inclusion in
collaboration and in conversations and
everything
there's going to be a lot of interesting
connections
and paths
um
and
it's being approached seemingly a
multiple layers like within the the two
layers that just we can focus most
narrowly on is like within the realm of
science
what is science
which is kind of like playing this other
um role with inertia
in some people's minds and in systems
what is science who gets to decide what
social science is I don't know I'm not
in social science
but it's system of interest to society
and certainly I'm a part of that
um so it's like what is the what is good
technically
what is social scientific
and then what is that social scientific
how does that gonna interface into the
the metaphysical questions and and the
normative ethical
and uh um decision making with
trade-offs and the real reflexive
complex decisions that matter
also while recognizing this increasingly
nuanced way of thinking about different
social intelligences
what's any other random thought or
curiosity about Collective Behavior
one point that I would have added into
the lecture
was just that in distributed systems
whether as modeled or as such
all behavior is arising from
interactions local to individuals even
if it's sent through some Wireless
mechanism it's like all about the local
interactions
and so that is a a an arising type
process
that gives the modeler like one
hands-off layer
at least if not much more another nice
feature about them
um they are in a way
ing to be composed because they
intrinsically contain like at least two
layers of consideration
not whether there's kind of like a
forcing function
of one layer and just sort of dangling a
bottom layer or whether there's a lot of
what we would call emergence or
discussive in in that way like that more
a rising function can be modeled but in
either way then you can kind of wrap
that two-layer system
and then compose them
so that's like what enables in certain
situations like parallelization
or at least you know that's obviously a
big area but that's what allows
multi-agent simulation Frameworks
to do
well on certain very challenging
sense making in action selection
problems not by guarantee or default
because any given slicing and dicing of
any given
um
prompting of information may not help
you adapt
but there are paths that do and don't
help
persist or not and that's this kind of
persistence
starting place that we
began with Sasha
um okay I really resonate with what you
mentioned about the local interactions
that um
even if information is transmitted
um over long distances
um then the agents
behave in a way that is locally relevant
and integrates that information
and it actually makes me think a lot
about the like psychology
um therapy angle that um while you uh
try to get information about uh the
person's like
um sort of local environment and
behavior
[Music]
um
or like perhaps you know demographics
and age that um they're informational
environment like a wealth of what kind
of um information they consume might
also be really telling about their
uh
psychological and like
Behavior Uh in interactions or
pathologies
um
and then to bring it kind of Full Circle
back to um that the
researcher is part of the ecosystem that
they are particip studying
um
yeah I I think it's just um
such a difference in perspective to see
that as like a positive and a gift that
um the way that you would design and run
an experiment today is not the way that
you would do it two years from now with
more experience and so
um that is a
a a benefit and like a bonus in the
system and not um like a negative
perspective of of bias that it's
detracting from some underlying uh truth
or reality
so just a few thoughts
oh very interesting anyone wanna
add something
I think we didn't fully resolve this
early question about the umbelt
um term from ethology behavioral
research observation science
using the term to describe the world as
it's experienced by a particular
organism
I think a few different pieces and
there's a lot of discussion and
discourse so just this is just even like
a super short overview the world we
might connect to World modeling
and there's a lot of interesting work in
all kinds of different like pros focus
on qualitative systems as well as some
artificial or synthetic intelligence
World modeling as it experienced as it
is experienced is one of the sticky and
deep ones because this is the area of
phenomenology and so this is like
a kind of semi-eternal discussion point
so whether whether active inference
delivers on world modeling is kind of
empirical and just plain
whereas as it is experienced is going to
be a philosophical question
and then by a particular organism that
specificity we get by actually making
the generative model
even if we're just speculating about it
it's like talking about experience
without an experiencer
would be like talk talking about um
some agent's Behavior without reference
to its niche
and then where there is like that
complex negotiation
I think the humanities and a lot of the
social sciences have identified
a lot of the
structural like top-down and also the
personal
bottom up
motifs of of things being
blurred and made complex
and so I think part of the social and
the scientific as coming only from the
scientific side
um is like to to
meet in the third space and or at least
make it work to have a mutual compromise
where it's like
certain social science social oriented
claims based upon this scientific
measure that is going to be a judgment
call
but understanding that conversation
where is it a mutual compromise in like
what dimensions not simply along the
kind of like rigor accessibility or
implications access there's just very
many things in play in these iterated
relationships in ecosystems
foreign
having a researcher as part of the
ecosystem
well what is it here's here's the
forager question you see the nest made
on the ground it's a forger but then we
step back it's like okay well it's
foraging
and then that's the allocation of the
forager then its foraging is still
part of this sense making this
generative sense making with like
process understanding
even of a Trace which is something that
Bruno LaTour and others have have
explored with like following a trace in
a social setting and using that to to
trace Networks
so in our digital ecosystems though our
information ecosystems
is not research happening
and so what what does that really mean
and then what are those social
normativities
there's going to be like a meeting or a
handoff with with where that really is
happening
or maybe it's a knocking on the door
that's ignores
or
it could be whatever metaphor in that
setting it actually is
there's no General metaphor because I'd
be like oh what's the general metaphor
on this experiment which experiment
just the general action that we plan to
take oh
hard to say
okay well in our last like connections I
guess
if anybody types a question live chat
we'll look at it otherwise what are any
other thoughts or like
what what
can we learn more about about Collective
Behavior
or what will it mean for our sense
making decision making if we understand
Collective Behavior better
what else are people excited about for
the rest of the course
like based upon the sections that we've
done so far
and and how how we can
even even start to approach this in in
an acknowledged Limited
finite way
yeah Sasha then than anyone else
just added a question to the very bottom
of the notes
um and it makes me think about
um how working on this document
collaboratively throughout the last hour
um we're able to uh kind of leave a
stigmergic trace of things we've
discussed and what sort of traits or
practices should
individual humans I guess I should
specify humans should we embody in order
to improve cohesion
um in Collective Behavior
it makes me think of certain psychology
um
traits or uh descriptions of like
openness
um or conscientiousness
um what will make
individual humans
um
better participants in
Collective Behavior
yeah I I think to to add to that
um
to just emphasize the importance again
only with
um human agents
um specifically if you have the capacity
to think and reflect and
the only ones that have that those uh
really Advanced capabilities that we
know of as yet but to really kind of
Leverage
um
in order to make the collective better
it is a responsibility on of the
individual
despite being
part of a collective and on in many
different on many different fronts to be
able to leverage and utilize their own
internal
States and what they have learned and to
be able to think
in a
to retain the individual the
individual's mind and think about the
collective
I think is so important it's the
collective is to
um
become healthier essentially to your
point and to improve its
yeah to become more
conscientious to become more
responsible or whatever that might be
so to always try and maintain a thinking
um
self is crucial
unless you can very easily be usurped
into the collective as it's
if you just go on any social media media
platform you will see
individuals rarely thinking
from themselves and seemingly kind of
just fueling each other and that that
causes massive problems
so an individual mind is strikes me as
being just the most important thing in
the future going forward
foreign
with individuation and collectivization
as these like ongoing
negotiated compromises that can be also
viewed many ways however however they
are
um
cognitive science coming into play
maybe uh historical processes
or
philosophies
were
um
used in many settings for
even approaching these kinds of social
questions
and now with computer science and
technology
it even like is a discussion more about
the capacities
of measurement and action
not that those are new in and of
themselves like but thinking like a
state like the development of the
apparatus
the development of the social social
systems that can be run on on Open
Source Hardware open source software
things like that
so
I I don't know if something's
generalized across all such groups
but
understanding what environments
at least initially things aren't
beginning at
is just a realist starting point
probably no guarantee since most things
slash all things are swept off the table
in their specifics anyway
so
and how to deal with that kind of like
skin on the line
type of decision making is very
interesting how it's pursued in the in
the Sciences
because often like many runs are
presented or that kind of like like
catastrophic failure mode of models is
is not considered just like part of the
training starting naive
um
so just the way the different social
considerations
are RR converged upon it's never it's
not like reduced to one
feature of the social because the social
is such an open space
as a scientist always impressed by how
that writing could kind of open up
the um
situations which are like mundane but
also of course Very
deep and meaningful
also though mundane
any other thoughts
or otherwise uh on on Collective
Behavior or on the social sciences
course or anything
otherwise people can have any lost words
if they want
yeah awesome thank you all for
participating
David want to add anything
yeah well I look forward to uh more
questions being asked on the course
website and everybody's um
engagement with the course is very much
appreciated so keep up the collective my
scale learning and it's it's a fun
course really happy that we could have
done this session and very happy to have
concluded the session
all right thank you bye bye everyone
ciao